<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->

<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5228 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5228.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5229 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5229.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5231 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5231.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3552 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3552.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc private="Pigeonhole Project" ?>

<rfc category="info" docName="spec-bosch-sieve-dict-lookup">
<!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

<front>
<title abbrev="Sieve External Data Extension">
Sieve Email Filtering: External Data Extension
</title>

<author fullname="Stephan Bosch" initials="S." surname="Bosch">
  <organization/>
  <address>
    <postal>
      <street></street>
      <city>Enschede</city>
      <country>NL</country>
    </postal>
    <email>stephan@rename-it.nl</email>
  </address>
</author>

<date month="January" year="2010" />

<area>General</area>
<workgroup>Pigeonhole Project</workgroup>
<keyword>sieve</keyword>
<keyword>dict</keyword>
<keyword>lookup</keyword>

<abstract>
<t>In advanced mail filtering setups, it is often convenient to store configuration
data in an external data store. This document updates the Sieve filtering language 
(RFC 5228) with an extension to support retrieving string values from external sources.
The extension supplies a new test so that external data can be examined. When the 
variables extension (RFC5229) is also active, the external data can also be accessed from
a special variables namespace. 
</t>
</abstract>
</front>

<middle>

<section title="Introduction">
<t>This is an extension to the Sieve language defined by <xref target="RFC5228">SIEVE</xref>. It
adds support for referencing externally stored named data. In the Sieve base specification such data
can only be made available in a Sieve script by including it statically in the Sieve script itself.
This extension adds a new test command to retrieve and evaluate data items stored externally. When
the <xref target="RFC5229">Sieve Variables extension</xref> is also active, a special variables
namespace is available through which the data items can be accessed more conveniently for string
substitution.</t>
<t>This extension is specific to the Pigeonhole Sieve implementation for the Dovecot Secure IMAP
server. It will therefore most likely not be supported by web interfaces and GUI-based ManageSieve 
clients. This extension is primarily meant for use in global scripts that are managed by the
systems administrator.</t>
</section>

<section title="Conventions Used in This Document">
<t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
<t>Conventions for notations are as in <xref target="RFC5228">SIEVE</xref> Section 1.1.</t>
</section>

<section title="Capability Identifier">
<t>The capability string associated with the extension defined in this document is
"vnd.dovecot.extdata".</t>
</section>

<section title="Naming of Data Items" anchor="naming">
<t>In the simplest case the name of a data store item is an identifier as defined in the 
<xref target="RFC5228">SIEVE</xref> grammar. For more complex situations, e.g. when multiple data
stores are available, the name can be structured hierarchically just like the namespace
syntax defined in <xref target="RFC5229">VARIABLES</xref>, with the restriction that numeric
(num-variable) elements are not allowed. This yields the following syntax for a data item name:
</t>
<figure>
<artwork><![CDATA[
data-item-name      =  identifier *("." identifier)
]]></artwork>
</figure>

</section>

<section title="Extdata Test">
<figure>
<artwork><![CDATA[
Usage:   extdata [COMPARATOR] [MATCH-TYPE]
                 <item-name: string>
                 <key-list: string-list>
]]></artwork>
</figure>

<t>The extdata test retrieves the data item specified by the item-name string from the external
data store and matches it to the values specified in the key-list argument. The specified item-name
MUST conform to the syntax defined in <xref target="naming"/>. The test succeeds if a match occurs. The type of 
match defaults to ":is" and the default comparator is "i;ascii-casemap".</t>

<t>The environment test MUST fail unconditionally if the specified data item cannot be retrieved,
e.g. because it does not exist in the external data store or when the data store is not available.
A script MUST NOT fail with an error if the item cannot be retrieved. This allows scripts to be 
written that handle nonexistent items gracefully.  In particular, the test:</t>

<figure>
<artwork><![CDATA[
  if extdata :contains "value" "" { ... }
]]></artwork>
</figure>

<t>only succeeds if "value" exists in the data store, and always succeeds if it is.</t>

<t>The <xref target="RFC5231">"relational" extension</xref> adds a match type called ":count".  The count of an
extdata test is 0 if the extdata information returned is the empty string, or 1 otherwise.</t>
</section>

<section title="Variables Namespace extdata">

<t>This document defines the variables namespace "extdata", as specified in <xref target="RFC5229">VARIABLES</xref>,
Section 3. The extdata namespace provides direct access to the data items in the external data store.</t>

<t>Example:</t>

<figure>
<artwork><![CDATA[
require ["vacation", "variables", "vnd.dovecot.extdata"];

vacation :subject "${extdata.vacation_subject}" 
         "${extdata.vacation_message}";
]]></artwork>
</figure>

<t>External data items accessed via the extdata test and the extdata variables namespace MUST be one and the same.  
The following example scripts are equivalent:</t>

<t>Example 1:</t>

<figure>
<artwork><![CDATA[
require ["fileinto", "variables", "vnd.dovecot.extdata"];

if allof (header :is "X-Spam-Status" "Yes",
  extdata :is "discard_spam" "yes") {
  discard;
} else {
  fileinto "Spam";
}
]]></artwork>
</figure>

<t>Example 2:</t>

<figure>
<artwork><![CDATA[
require ["fileinto", variables", "vnd.dovecot.extdata"];

if allof (header :is "X-Spam-Status" "Yes",
  string :is "${extdata.discard_spam}" "yes") {
  discard;
} else {
  fileinto "Spam";
}
]]></artwork>
</figure>

<t>The extdata namespace accepts any identifier as variable name. A script MUST NOT 
fail with an error when a data item is referenced that does not exist in the external
data store or otherwise cannot be retrieved. In that case the empty string will be 
substituted, which is analogous to the substitution of unset normal variables. Use
the extdata test to evaluate wether a data item exists and can be retrieved. 
</t>

<t>This extension only concerns the retrieval of external data items and therefore
it is not possible to assign values to items within the extdata variables namespace using
for example the "set" action defined in <xref target="RFC5229">VARIABLES</xref>. A
script MUST fail with an error when an attempt is made to assign to an item in the
extdata namespace. 
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
<t>Martin F. Foster provided the original idea for this extension.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
<t>Administrators should keep in mind that retrieving values from an external
data store can reveal more data to a user than strictly allowed when the data
store is not queried carefully. 
</t>
</section>
</middle>

<!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

<back>
<!-- References split into informative and normative -->

<references title="Normative References">
  &RFC2119;
  &RFC5228;
  &RFC5229;
  &RFC5231;
</references>

<!-- <references title="Informative References">
  &RFC3552;
 </references> -->
</back>

</rfc>
